<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
	<title>Lexicon of Song</title>
	<description>Examining the meanings and workings of great songs</description>
	<link>https://lexiconofsong.org</link>
	<language>en-us</language>
	<managingEditor>hb@lexiconofsong.org (Herb Bowie)</managingEditor>
	<webMaster>hb@lexiconofsong.org (Herb Bowie)</webMaster>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2022 00:00 PDT</lastBuildDate>
	<pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2022 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
	<atom:link href="https://lexiconofsong/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<ttl>1440</ttl>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Angel from Montgomery&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/angel-from-montgomery.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/angel-from-montgomery.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2022 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This song was released on John Prine&amp;#8217;s first, self-titled, album, when the singer-songwriter was just twenty-five years of age. Prine grew up near Chicago, and studied at that city&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oldtownschool.org&quot;&gt;Old Town School of Folk Music&lt;/a&gt; (a fine establishment I&amp;#8217;ve visited several times, and one that is still delivering concerts and classes today). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prine was working as a mailman before turning to music as a full-time career. He remembers delivering newspapers to a Baptist old peoples home where he had to go room-to-room, and there developed something of an affinity for our aging population. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These memories and observations led him to write a song called &amp;#8220;Hello In There&amp;#8221; for that first album. A friend liked that song so much that he suggested Prine write &amp;#8220;another song about old people.&amp;#8221; And that suggestion led Prine to pen &amp;#8220;Angel from Montgomery,&amp;#8221; pulling the song&amp;#8217;s words and images from some deeper reservoir. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Long Black Veil&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/long-black-veil.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/long-black-veil.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;My earliest memory of this song is hearing it on the first album by The Band, &lt;em&gt;Music from Big Pink&lt;/em&gt;, back in 1968. I understood then that this was the one song on the album that was written neither by members of The Band nor by Bob Dylan, but didn&amp;#8217;t know much else about it at the time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, a few years later, I discovered that it was one of the few songs that my father and I both knew, and could play together on our guitars. Turned out he had probably heard it as recorded by The Country Gentlemen on their 1960 album, &lt;em&gt;Country Songs Old &amp;amp; New&lt;/em&gt;, or had simply heard this same group perform the song at one of their many shows at the Crossroads, outside of DC, a venue my dad was known to have frequented. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, I found the song included on the Rosanne Cash album &lt;em&gt;The List&lt;/em&gt;, the title referring to a list of essential American songs as identified by &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt; father, Johnny Cash. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, later, it just started to turn up everywhere. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Settin&apos; the Woods on Fire&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/settinapos-the-woods-on-fire.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/settinapos-the-woods-on-fire.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;A couple of things that happened recently got me cogitating on the idea of language as playground. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I had a chance to hear &lt;a href=&quot;https://acurzan.english.lsa.umich.edu&quot;&gt;Anne Curzan&lt;/a&gt; speak. Curzan is the talented and engaging dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts at the University of Michigan (my alma mater), and is also a linguist who studies the history of the English language. Her bio states that she &amp;#8220;aims to promote a culture based in purpose and contributing to the common good, the power of learning, &lt;em&gt;the value of play&lt;/em&gt; [emphasis mine], and the importance of well-being.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I&amp;#8217;m here to tell you: any time you stir together the value of play and the study of the English language in the same pitcher, you&amp;#8217;re mixing up a cocktail that I will happily imbibe. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;And When I Die&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/and-when-i-die.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/and-when-i-die.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;As children, our thoughts about death are stuff of dreams and fairy tales. As adults we learn to suppress these thoughts because we are busy getting on with things. But as teenagers, in this transition between nursery rhymes and real life, we tend to approach this topic with a frankness and curiosity that can be somewhat startling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laura Nyro wrote her song &amp;#8220;And When I Die&amp;#8221; at the age of 17, and her refreshing treatment of the subject shows none of the reverence or piety that we learn to adopt as adults. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s look over her lyrics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when I die and when I&amp;#8217;m dead, dead and gone,   &lt;br /&gt;
There&amp;#8217;ll be one child born and a world to carry on, to carry on.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m not scared of dying and I don&amp;#8217;t really care.   &lt;br /&gt;
If it&amp;#8217;s peace you find in dying, well, then let the time be near.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Hallelujah&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/hallelujah.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/hallelujah.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;The history of Leonard Cohen&amp;#8217;s song &amp;#8220;Hallelujah&amp;#8221; is a fascinating one. Cohen&amp;#8217;s songs had never really been embraced by the masses, and his first recording of &amp;#8220;Hallelujah&amp;#8221; in the early eighties was part of an album so lacking in obvious commercial appeal that the president of CBS Records responded to it by saying: &amp;#8220;What is this? This isn&amp;#8217;t pop music. We&amp;#8217;re not releasing it. This is a disaster.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That recording was released, however, a little later on a small independent label, but few people took note of the album or of this particular song. Even for Cohen&amp;#8217;s small set of fans, it did not seem like a particularly memorable recording. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then a funny series of events began to play out over the next couple of decades. John Cale, formerly of the Velvet Underground, and himself not a household name, recorded a version of the song for a Cohen tribute album in 1991. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;The Weight&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/the-weight.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/the-weight.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I recently came across the Playing for Change &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/ph1GU1qQ1zQ&quot;&gt;Song Around the World video&lt;/a&gt; of Robbie Robertson&amp;#8217;s composition &amp;#8220;The Weight,&amp;#8221; and it made me want to think &amp;#8211; and write! &amp;#8211; more deeply about how this song works, and what it means, and the timeless nature of its appeal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s just read the lyrics through first (and listen to the music), and then talk about it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled into Nazareth,    &lt;br /&gt;
Was feeling about half past dead.    &lt;br /&gt;
I just need some place     &lt;br /&gt;
Where I can lay my head.    &lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Hey, mister, can you tell me     &lt;br /&gt;
Where a man might find a bed?&quot;    &lt;br /&gt;
He just grinned and shook my hand,    &lt;br /&gt;
&amp;#8220;No&amp;#8221; was all he said.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a load off Fanny.    &lt;br /&gt;
Take a load for free.      &lt;br /&gt;
Take a load off Fanny,     &lt;br /&gt;
And (and) (and) you put the load right on me.    &lt;br /&gt;
(You put the load right on me)    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up my bag,   &lt;br /&gt;
I went looking for a place to hide.    &lt;br /&gt;
When I saw Carmen and the Devil    &lt;br /&gt;
Walking side by side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;800 Pound Jesus&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/800-pound-jesus.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/800-pound-jesus.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2019 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;d been aware of Paul Thorn for some time, but didn&amp;#8217;t really become a fan until I saw him live last summer at The Ark in Ann Arbor. I convinced an old University of Michigan roommate to come with me while I was in town, as an opportunity to catch up, but we were both caught off guard by how much we loved Thorn&amp;#8217;s show. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been listening to Thorn&amp;#8217;s recordings regularly since then, and can now bear witness to a great catalog that stands up to deep and repeated listening.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musically Thorn reminds me of Delbert McClinton and a few other artists who have somewhat belatedly been collected under the &lt;em&gt;Americana&lt;/em&gt; banner. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Fruitcakes&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/fruitcakes.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/fruitcakes.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2018 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;From the Dictionary app on my iMac: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;fruitcake: 1. A cake containing dried fruit and nuts.2. (informal) an eccentric or insane person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve always considered &amp;#8220;Fruitcakes&amp;#8221; to be Jimmy Buffet&amp;#8217;s masterwork. The musical backing is infectious, swaying and danceable, and the background vocals add depth. The words are cleverly crafted, and perfectly suited to Buffett&amp;#8217;s conversational, wisecracking delivery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song is from 1993, and contains some dated references, but these just add to the fun for me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The singer starts with a spoken introduction, setting up the verses that will follow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know I was talking to my friend Desdemona the other day. She runs this space station bake shop down near Boomtown. She told me that human beings are flawed individuals, that the cosmic bakers took us out of the oven a little too early, and that&amp;#8217;s the reason we&amp;#8217;re as crazy as we are, and I believe it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note what Buffett is doing here. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;The Village Green Preservation Society&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/the-village-green-preservation-society.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/the-village-green-preservation-society.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This is a rather amazing song by The Kinks, first released in 1968. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved this song from the moment I first heard it, but my appreciation for it has only grown over the years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the same year that John Lennon and Yoko Ono released an album called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unfinished_Music_No._1:_Two_Virgins&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two Virgins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (certainly using the term to refer to themselves metaphorically, not literally), with an album cover showing the two artists completely naked, Ray Davies wrote a song with the immortal line, &amp;#8220;God save little shops, china cups and virginity&amp;#8221; (and Davies, to be clear,  delivered this line quite seriously and quite literally); &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Will the Circle be Unbroken&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/will-the-circle-be-unbroken.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/will-the-circle-be-unbroken.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I first heard this song as the title track on the monumental 1972 album by the Nitty Gritty Dirt Band, which they recorded with a number of country music greats who were still alive at the time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This song is usually recorded under the title of &amp;#8220;Will the Circle be Unbroken,&amp;#8221; but it&amp;#8217;s also known by the name &amp;#8220;Can the Circle be Unbroken.&amp;#8221; The song was the result of a reworking by A.P. Carter of the hymn &amp;#8220;Will the Circle be Unbroken?.&amp;#8221; The song was first released in 1935, on a single by the Carter Family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of wonderful recordings of this song that I can recommend. I&amp;#8217;ll list them in chronological sequence. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Girl From The North Country&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/girl-from-the-north-country.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/girl-from-the-north-country.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2017 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This is a deft example of the songwriter&amp;#8217;s art. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dylan has such an inimitable bag of tricks that many of his songs are unmistakably marked as his, either through attitude, theme, use of language, unusual length, or some combination of these factors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, though, Dylan is like a master magician: even after you&amp;#8217;ve taken away all the props, and had him roll up his sleeves, he can still effortlessly reach behind your ear and come back with a gold doubloon in his hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No railing against authority here, no diverse, divergent set of cultural references, no rolling series of verses, no hallucinatory imagery, no put-downs, no fancy words. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet Dylan still manages to produce a masterpiece. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s review the lyrics. It won&amp;#8217;t take long. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;If I Had a Boat&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/if-i-had-a-boat.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/if-i-had-a-boat.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2015 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This has always been my favorite Lyle Lovett recording. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The singer starts with the chorus, which is then repeated after each verse. Both musically and lyrically, it starts out as a simple children&amp;#8217;s song, with gentle, bright finger-picking on the guitar. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had a boat,  &lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;#8217;d go out on the ocean.  &lt;br /&gt;
And if I had a pony,   &lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;#8217;d ride him on my boat.  &lt;br /&gt;
And we could all together  &lt;br /&gt;
go out on the ocean,  &lt;br /&gt;
Me upon my pony on my boat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chorus is clearly from the perspective of a young child. Each line is simple and short, the rhyming consisting only of the repeated use of the word &amp;#8220;boat.&amp;#8221; Note that Lovett&amp;#8217;s singing is straightforward, sincere and heartfelt. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the first verse, though, Lovett shifts gears, taking a slightly older, more ironic perspective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I were Roy Rogers,  &lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;#8217;d sure enough be single.   &lt;br /&gt;
I couldn&amp;#8217;t bring myself to marrying old Dale.   &lt;br /&gt;
It&amp;#8217;d just be me and Trigger.  &lt;br /&gt;
We&amp;#8217;d go riding through them movies,   &lt;br /&gt;
Then we&amp;#8217;d buy a boat and on the sea we&amp;#8217;d sail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;For What It&apos;s Worth&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/for-what-itaposs-worth.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/for-what-itaposs-worth.html</guid>
		<pubDate>2001</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;The beginning of the song is a study in understatement. An electric guitar plays two notes, slowly repeated, with tremolo. The drums set up a quiet pulse-like beat. An acoustic guitar enters, strumming two chords, then beginning a quiet riff that is a definition of laid-back L.A. funk. Finally Steve Stills&amp;#8217; voice enters, in a quiet, conversational tone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s something happening here.  &lt;br /&gt;
What it is ain&amp;#8217;t exactly clear.  &lt;br /&gt;
There&amp;#8217;s a man with a gun over there,  &lt;br /&gt;
Telling me I got to beware.  &lt;br /&gt;
I think it&amp;#8217;s time we stop, children, what&amp;#8217;s that sound?  &lt;br /&gt;
Everybody look what&amp;#8217;s going down.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how the first two lines draw the listener in and create suspense. The singer says that &amp;#8220;something is happening,&amp;#8221; but we don&amp;#8217;t yet have any idea what it is. The next two lines up the ante &amp;#8211; saying that there is a &amp;#8220;man with a gun&amp;#8221; involved &amp;#8211; but maintain the suspense, since we don&amp;#8217;t know who the man is, why he has a gun, or what he intends to do with it. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
