<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
	<title>Lexicon of Song</title>
	<description>Examining the meanings and workings of great songs</description>
	<link>https://lexiconofsong.org</link>
	<language>en-us</language>
	<managingEditor>hb@lexiconofsong.org (Herb Bowie)</managingEditor>
	<webMaster>hb@lexiconofsong.org (Herb Bowie)</webMaster>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 10:21 PDT</lastBuildDate>
	<pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 10:21 PDT</pubDate>
	<atom:link href="https://lexiconofsong/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<ttl>1440</ttl>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;1952 Vincent Black Lightning&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/1952-vincent-black-lightning.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/1952-vincent-black-lightning.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This is a song by English singer/songwriter/guitarist Richard Thompson. It was first released on his album &lt;em&gt;Rumor and Sigh&lt;/em&gt; in 1991, but has since because a staple of his live shows — and I actually prefer some of the live renditions to the original studio version. The song was never released as a single, and so was never a hit for the general public, but it’s an easy song to appreciate, and I’ve never seen anyone give it a listen without at least liking it quite a bit. And many — including this author — believe it to be a classic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helps to understand that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vincent_Black_Lightning&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Vincent Black Lightning&lt;/a&gt; was a real motorcycle, and a very special machine. It was produced in England from 1948 – 1952, and was designed to be as fast as possible. It broke the motorcycle land speed record of the time, going over 150 miles per hour. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Desperados Under the Eaves&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/desperados-under-the-eaves.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/desperados-under-the-eaves.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 16:00 PST</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I’ve been wondering lately why I’ve never written an appreciation for any of Warren Zevon’s songs. It’s certainly not that he didn’t give us many great tracks to choose from. Upon reflection, perhaps it’s because he wrote so many compact little gems that it’s hard to pick just one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the reason, this song of his has been haunting me lately, so it’s time to correct the omission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of Zevon’s genius as a lyricist was his ability to invest ordinary material objects with such deep feelings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This song is an outstanding example. It’s so simple, so short, and yet the words and images resonate like stones skipped onto the water, with meaning spreading out in expanding ripples. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to share the lyrics in their entirety before commenting — and, of course, I encourage you to listen to Zevon’s recording as well.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was sitting in the Hollywood Hawaiian Hotel;  &lt;br /&gt;
I was staring in my empty coffee cup. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Step by Step&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/step-by-step.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/step-by-step.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allmusic.com/artist/jesse-winchester-mn0000339905&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Jesse Winchester&lt;/a&gt; fan ever since I slipped his first album onto my turntable in my dorm room back in Ann Arbor, but somehow I don&amp;#8217;t think I&amp;#8217;d paid much attention to this gem until I stumbled across it yesterday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fits neatly into Winchester&amp;#8217;s small but accomplished set of songs about god and religion — songs like &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&quot;quiet-about-it.html&quot; class=&quot;wiki-link&quot;&gt;Quiet About It&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;Isn&amp;#8217;t That So?&amp;#8221;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I love about this group of Winchester songs is that he displays obvious familiarity with, and even sympathy for, the Christian tradition, but manages to bring an entirely fresh approach to his questioning of these sacred topics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This song seems to start with the picture painted by the spiritual &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/When_the_Saints_Go_Marching_In&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;When The Saints Go Marching In&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;#8221; and then picks up from there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give a listen to the Winchester recording, then stroll with me through the lyrics. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Ring Them Bells&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/ring-them-bells.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/ring-them-bells.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This is a gem of a Dylan song: not a big, gaudy rock, but a modest yet finely wrought masterpiece. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was released in 1989 on his album &lt;em&gt;Oh Mercy&lt;/em&gt;, so it&amp;#8217;s not from any of his early years, during which his work was more consistently revered. The album was produced by Daniel Lanois, and critics are somewhat divided over the success of his efforts in rendering Dylan&amp;#8217;s voice and compositions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find the original version by Dylan to be pretty underwhelming, but the song came alive for me when I heard it performed by Sarah Jarosz. She recorded it on her second album, &lt;em&gt;Follow Me Down&lt;/em&gt;, from 2011, and she&amp;#8217;s included it consistently in the several live shows of hers that I&amp;#8217;ve seen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me the Dylan version seems a bit slow and somnolent, while the Jarosz version feels much more spirited. Partly, I suppose, it&amp;#8217;s the difference between the performance of a world-weary man approaching the half-century mark, working on his 26th album, versus a youthful 20-year old working on her second. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Pancho and Lefty&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/pancho-and-lefty.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/pancho-and-lefty.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve already written about &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&quot;long-black-veil.html&quot; class=&quot;wiki-link&quot;&gt;Long Black Veil&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;#8221; which was one one of my father&amp;#8217;s favorite songs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;#8217;m probably overdue to write about &amp;#8220;Pancho and Lefty,&amp;#8221; which was one of my father-in-law&amp;#8217;s favorites &amp;#8211; and one of mine as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit like &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&quot;hallelujah.html&quot; class=&quot;wiki-link&quot;&gt;Hallelujah&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;#8221; by Leonard Cohen, this song seems to have had an interesting life of its own. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was written by Townes Van Zandt, a legendary Texan singer/songwriter, and first released on his album &lt;em&gt;The Late Great Townes Van Zandt&lt;/em&gt; back in 1972.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither the song nor the album received a whole lot of attention at the time, let alone any accolades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then Emmylou Harris recorded it on her album &lt;em&gt;Luxury Liner&lt;/em&gt; in 1977, giving the song a bit more exposure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, finally, Willie Nelson and Merle Haggard recorded it in 1983, and released it as a single, which promptly became a huge hit for the pair. As the story goes, Willie Nelson&amp;#8217;s daughter introduced the song to them. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;They All Laughed&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/they-all-laughed.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/they-all-laughed.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I first heard this song as part of the soundtrack to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/They_All_Laughed&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;movie with the same name&lt;/a&gt;, made by Peter Bogdanovich in 1981. The movie is worth watching, if you like quirky (as I generally do), but it was the song that stuck with me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was really my introduction to the songs of George and Ira Gershwin, with George supplying the music, and brother Ira providing the lyrics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of their songs have become recognized as part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_American_Songbook&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Great American Songbook&lt;/a&gt;, but Ira&amp;#8217;s lyrics are often too subtle and offbeat to fit cleanly into that mold. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This song, in particular, is one that is less frequently sung. Supposedly playwright and producer George S. Kaufman heard an early rehearsal of the number and wondered whether it was, in fact, a love song at all, before the brothers finally got to the lyric “They laughed at me wanting you,” at which point Kaufman threw up his hands and said, “Oh, well. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;When I Paint My Masterpiece&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/when-i-paint-my-masterpiece.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/when-i-paint-my-masterpiece.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2023 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been reading Rick Rubin&amp;#8217;s book &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/717356/the-creative-act-by-rick-rubin/&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;The Creative Act: A Way of Being&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; lately &amp;#8211; not all at once, mind you, but sipping it slowly, like a rare old whiskey &amp;#8211; and it&amp;#8217;s put me in mind of this song by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bobdylan.com&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Bob Dylan&lt;/a&gt;, from 1971. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This composition has been performed and recorded by Dylan himself on multiple occasions, but the first released recording was by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reasontorock.com/artists/band.html&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;The Band&lt;/a&gt;, and their &lt;a href=&quot;https://music.apple.com/us/album/when-i-paint-my-masterpiece-remastered/1440841468?i=1440841881&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;original studio recording&lt;/a&gt; is still the version I&amp;#8217;m partial to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s just review the lyrics, shall we? Ideally, of course, along with the music. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, the streets of Rome are filled with rubble.  &lt;br /&gt;
Ancient footprints are everywhere. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Train to Birmingham&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/train-to-birmingham.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/train-to-birmingham.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 16:00 PST</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;Southerner Thomas Wolfe, in his book &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_Can%27t_Go_Home_Again&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;You Can&amp;#8217;t Go Home Again&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, had his main character  speak these words: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;#8217;t go back home to your family, back home to your childhood &amp;#8230; back home to a young man&amp;#8217;s dreams of glory and of fame &amp;#8230; back home to places in the country, back home to the old forms and systems of things which once seemed everlasting, but which are changing all the time – back home to the escapes of Time and Memory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Hiatt seemed to have had much the same sentiments in mind when he penned his song &amp;#8220;Train to Birmingham.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several others have recorded this composition, but Hiatt&amp;#8217;s own version seems to me to be the definitive rendition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the eighth track from the album &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3wRne18&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Dirty Jeans and Mudslide Hymns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; starts up, note how the rhythm of the drums gives you a seat on the train before Hiatt even opens his mouth. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Whenever Kindness Fails&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/whenever-kindness-fails.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/whenever-kindness-fails.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 16:00 PST</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been thinking a lot lately about this song by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.robertearlkeen.com&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Robert Earl Keen&lt;/a&gt;, first recorded by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ely.com&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Joe Ely&lt;/a&gt; for his &lt;em&gt;Love and Danger&lt;/em&gt; album, released in 1992. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is &amp;#8211; be advised &amp;#8211; a &lt;em&gt;difficult&lt;/em&gt; song, in that the narrator talks about shooting and killing people, and tries to justify his actions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So before I start sharing my thoughts, perhaps it is best to issue a clarification that no one here is advocating for any kind of gun violence. Heck, I don&amp;#8217;t even &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; a gun. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is a great song. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consider both Joe Ely&amp;#8217;s version and the later recording by the songwriter himself to be excellent renditions, so feel free to listen to either, or both. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, let&amp;#8217;s dive into the words. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I crossed the desert in a dining car,  &lt;br /&gt;
In the spring of ninety-one.  &lt;br /&gt;
I met some people drinking at the bar,  &lt;br /&gt;
They were laughing, having fun.  &lt;br /&gt;
I told &apos;em that I hadn&amp;#8217;t heard the joke  &lt;br /&gt;
That was so hilarious. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Shady Grove&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/shady-grove.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/shady-grove.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This is a traditional Appalachian folk song believed to have originated in eastern Kentucky around the beginning of the 20th century. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The melody seems to have come from the ballad &amp;#8220;Matty Groves,&amp;#8221; and probably started out in England or Scotland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re a child of the sixties like me, then your introduction to the song may have come though the electrified adaptation by Quicksilver Messenger Service, but it is more typically performed in acoustic folk, country or bluegrass styles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the features that draws me to this song is its elusive, shape-shifting nature. As in a dream, very specific, concrete images appear and then are replaced with others, leaving the singer/listener/dreamer free to choose the meanings they associate with these word pictures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This elusive quality begins with the title itself, which sounds like the name or description of a place, and yet is often used in the song as if it were the name of a woman. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;I Don&apos;t Like Half The Folks I Love&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/i-donapost-like-half-the-folks-i-love.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/i-donapost-like-half-the-folks-i-love.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve spent some time lately working my way through &lt;em&gt;The Dawn of Everything: A New History of Humanity&lt;/em&gt;, by Davids Graeber and Wengrow. It&amp;#8217;s a fascinating book, and a really rewarding read, but it&amp;#8217;s also a serious tome, clocking in at over 500 pages of text dense with facts and ideas, so it&amp;#8217;s not something I&amp;#8217;ve been attempting all at one go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, as I was reading the latest chapter last night I came across this surprising observation: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an obvious objection to evolutionary models which assume that our strongest social ties are based on close biological kinship: many humans just don&amp;#8217;t like their families very much. And this appears to be just as true of present-day hunter-gatherers as anybody else. Many seem to find the prospect of living their entire lives surrounded by close relatives so unpleasant that they will travel very long distances just to get away from them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;The Last Trip to Tulsa&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/the-last-trip-to-tulsa.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/the-last-trip-to-tulsa.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This song has been on my mind a lot lately, so I decided to research and write about it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s certainly an outlier in the Neil Young songbook. It closed out Young&amp;#8217;s first, self-titled, solo album, with a running time of close to ten minutes. This was an album my friends and I pretty much wore out in our dorm rooms, listening to it when it first came out, so I&amp;#8217;ve been familiar with it for a long time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A live recording of the song was released in 2008 as part of the &lt;em&gt;Sugar Mountain: Live at Canterbury House 1968&lt;/em&gt; album, and I actually prefer this version. For one, it includes a couple of lines that add to the song, that were missing from the earlier studio recording; for another, Young&amp;#8217;s vocals seem purer and less strained in the intimate coffee house setting. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Come On Up to the House&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/come-on-up-to-the-house.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/come-on-up-to-the-house.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This song was written by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tomwaits.com&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Tom Waits&lt;/a&gt;, and his performance of the song on his 1999 album &lt;em&gt;Mule Variations&lt;/em&gt; is certainly worth hearing. His delivery sounds like that of a down-at-the-heels preacher delivering the holy message at a revival meeting, or perhaps on a street corner, with a Salvation Army style brass band playing in the background. He delivers his sermon with an unarguable power and authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My introduction to the song, however, came during the encore performance by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sarahjarosz.com&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Sarah Jarosz&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tractortavern.com&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Tractor Tavern&lt;/a&gt; a couple of years ago. I can still remember the looks on the faces of Sarah and her band as they delivered the song to the standing, swaying crowd, seemingly amazed at the depth of feeling and the bond between performer and audience being wrought within the house that night, as all present returned again and again to the chorus with increasing emotional commitment. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Angel from Montgomery&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/angel-from-montgomery.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/angel-from-montgomery.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This song was released on John Prine&amp;#8217;s first, self-titled, album, when the singer-songwriter was just twenty-five years of age. Prine grew up near Chicago, and studied at that city&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oldtownschool.org&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Old Town School of Folk Music&lt;/a&gt; (a fine establishment I&amp;#8217;ve visited several times, and one that is still delivering concerts and classes today). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prine was working as a mailman before turning to music as a full-time career. He remembers delivering newspapers to a Baptist old peoples home where he had to go room-to-room, and there developed something of an affinity for our aging population. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These memories and observations led him to write a song called &amp;#8220;Hello In There&amp;#8221; for that first album. A friend liked that song so much that he suggested Prine write &amp;#8220;another song about old people.&amp;#8221; And that suggestion led Prine to pen &amp;#8220;Angel from Montgomery,&amp;#8221; pulling the song&amp;#8217;s words and images from some deeper reservoir. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Long Black Veil&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/long-black-veil.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/long-black-veil.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;My earliest memory of this song is hearing it on the first album by The Band, &lt;em&gt;Music from Big Pink&lt;/em&gt;, back in 1968. I understood then that this was the one song on the album that was written neither by members of The Band nor by Bob Dylan, but didn&amp;#8217;t know much else about it at the time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, a few years later, I discovered that it was one of the few songs that my father and I both knew, and could play together on our guitars. Turned out he had probably heard it as recorded by The Country Gentlemen on their 1960 album, &lt;em&gt;Country Songs Old &amp;amp; New&lt;/em&gt;, or had simply heard this same group perform the song at one of their many shows at the Crossroads, outside of DC, a venue my dad was known to have frequented. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, I found the song included on the Rosanne Cash album &lt;em&gt;The List&lt;/em&gt;, the title referring to a list of essential American songs as identified by &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt; father, Johnny Cash. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, later, it just started to turn up everywhere. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Settin&apos; the Woods on Fire&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/settinapos-the-woods-on-fire.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/settinapos-the-woods-on-fire.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;A couple of things that happened recently got me cogitating on the idea of language as playground. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I had a chance to hear &lt;a href=&quot;https://acurzan.english.lsa.umich.edu&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Anne Curzan&lt;/a&gt; speak. Curzan is the talented and engaging dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts at the University of Michigan (my alma mater), and is also a linguist who studies the history of the English language. Her bio states that she &amp;#8220;aims to promote a culture based in purpose and contributing to the common good, the power of learning, &lt;em&gt;the value of play&lt;/em&gt; [emphasis mine], and the importance of well-being.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I&amp;#8217;m here to tell you: any time you stir together the value of play and the study of the English language in the same pitcher, you&amp;#8217;re mixing up a cocktail that I will happily imbibe. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;And When I Die&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/and-when-i-die.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/and-when-i-die.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;As children, our thoughts about death are stuff of dreams and fairy tales. As adults we learn to suppress these thoughts because we are busy getting on with things. But as teenagers, in this transition between nursery rhymes and real life, we tend to approach this topic with a frankness and curiosity that can be somewhat startling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laura Nyro wrote her song &amp;#8220;And When I Die&amp;#8221; at the age of 17, and her refreshing treatment of the subject shows none of the reverence or piety that we learn to adopt as adults. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s look over her lyrics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when I die and when I&amp;#8217;m dead, dead and gone,   &lt;br /&gt;
There&amp;#8217;ll be one child born and a world to carry on, to carry on.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m not scared of dying and I don&amp;#8217;t really care.   &lt;br /&gt;
If it&amp;#8217;s peace you find in dying, well, then let the time be near. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Christmas Song by Dave Matthews&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/christmas-song-by-dave-matthews.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/christmas-song-by-dave-matthews.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 16:00 PST</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;Like Robbie Robertson and The Band, Dave Matthews seeks here to craft a retelling of the story of Jesus that might cause us to look at this old tale from a fresh perspective, and consider anew its core meaning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This retelling is a bit more ambitious than Robertson&amp;#8217;s. Like Jackson Browne, Matthews is not an avowed Christian, and yet he finds deep meaning in this story. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several recordings of this song by Dave and his companions, including several live versions. One I particularly like is the one by Dave and his friend Tim Reynolds, performed live at Luther College.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song opens with a descending guitar figure that is repeated throughout the song. It&amp;#8217;s a very simple but distinctive riff, pretty but serious, and ending with a pause that seems to hang in the air, as if waiting for an answer to a question. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Hallelujah&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/hallelujah.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/hallelujah.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;The history of Leonard Cohen&amp;#8217;s song &amp;#8220;Hallelujah&amp;#8221; is a fascinating one. Cohen&amp;#8217;s songs had never really been embraced by the masses, and his first recording of &amp;#8220;Hallelujah&amp;#8221; in the early eighties was part of an album so lacking in obvious commercial appeal that the president of CBS Records responded to it by saying: &amp;#8220;What is this? This isn&amp;#8217;t pop music. We&amp;#8217;re not releasing it. This is a disaster.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That recording was released, however, a little later on a small independent label, but few people took note of the album or of this particular song. Even for Cohen&amp;#8217;s small set of fans, it did not seem like a particularly memorable recording. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then a funny series of events began to play out over the next couple of decades. John Cale, formerly of the Velvet Underground, and himself not a household name, recorded a version of the song for a Cohen tribute album in 1991. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;The Weight&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/the-weight.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/the-weight.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2020 17:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I recently came across the Playing for Change &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/ph1GU1qQ1zQ&quot; class=&quot;ext-link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Song Around the World video&lt;/a&gt; of Robbie Robertson&amp;#8217;s composition &amp;#8220;The Weight,&amp;#8221; and it made me want to think &amp;#8211; and write! &amp;#8211; more deeply about how this song works, and what it means, and the timeless nature of its appeal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s just read the lyrics through first (and listen to the music), and then talk about it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled into Nazareth,    &lt;br /&gt;
Was feeling about half past dead.    &lt;br /&gt;
I just need some place     &lt;br /&gt;
Where I can lay my head.    &lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Hey, mister, can you tell me     &lt;br /&gt;
Where a man might find a bed?&quot;    &lt;br /&gt;
He just grinned and shook my hand,    &lt;br /&gt;
&amp;#8220;No&amp;#8221; was all he said.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a load off Fanny.    &lt;br /&gt;
Take a load for free.      &lt;br /&gt;
Take a load off Fanny,     &lt;br /&gt;
And (and) (and) you put the load right on me.    &lt;br /&gt;
(You put the load right on me)    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up my bag,   &lt;br /&gt;
I went looking for a place to hide.    &lt;br /&gt;
When I saw Carmen and the Devil    &lt;br /&gt;
Walking side by side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
