<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
	<title>Lexicon of Song</title>
	<description>Examining the meanings and workings of great songs</description>
	<link>https://lexiconofsong.org</link>
	<language>en-us</language>
	<managingEditor>hb@lexiconofsong.org (Herb Bowie)</managingEditor>
	<webMaster>hb@lexiconofsong.org (Herb Bowie)</webMaster>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00 PDT</lastBuildDate>
	<pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
	<atom:link href="https://lexiconofsong/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<ttl>1440</ttl>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Come On Up to the House&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/come-on-up-to-the-house.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/come-on-up-to-the-house.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2022 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This song was written by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tomwaits.com&quot;&gt;Tom Waits&lt;/a&gt;, and his performance of the song on his 1999 album &lt;em&gt;Mule Variations&lt;/em&gt; is certainly worth hearing. His delivery sounds like that of a down-at-the-heels preacher delivering the holy message at a revival meeting, or perhaps on a street corner, with a Salvation Army style brass band playing in the background. He delivers his sermon with an unarguable power and authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My introduction to the song, however, came during the encore performance by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sarahjarosz.com&quot;&gt;Sarah Jarosz&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tractortavern.com&quot;&gt;Tractor Tavern&lt;/a&gt; a couple of years ago. I can still remember the looks on the faces of Sarah and her band as they delivered the song to the standing, swaying crowd, seemingly amazed at the depth of feeling and the bond between performer and audience being wrought within the house that night, as all present returned again and again to the chorus with increasing emotional commitment. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Angel from Montgomery&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/angel-from-montgomery.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/angel-from-montgomery.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2022 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This song was released on John Prine&amp;#8217;s first, self-titled, album, when the singer-songwriter was just twenty-five years of age. Prine grew up near Chicago, and studied at that city&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oldtownschool.org&quot;&gt;Old Town School of Folk Music&lt;/a&gt; (a fine establishment I&amp;#8217;ve visited several times, and one that is still delivering concerts and classes today). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prine was working as a mailman before turning to music as a full-time career. He remembers delivering newspapers to a Baptist old peoples home where he had to go room-to-room, and there developed something of an affinity for our aging population. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These memories and observations led him to write a song called &amp;#8220;Hello In There&amp;#8221; for that first album. A friend liked that song so much that he suggested Prine write &amp;#8220;another song about old people.&amp;#8221; And that suggestion led Prine to pen &amp;#8220;Angel from Montgomery,&amp;#8221; pulling the song&amp;#8217;s words and images from some deeper reservoir. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Long Black Veil&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/long-black-veil.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/long-black-veil.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;My earliest memory of this song is hearing it on the first album by The Band, &lt;em&gt;Music from Big Pink&lt;/em&gt;, back in 1968. I understood then that this was the one song on the album that was written neither by members of The Band nor by Bob Dylan, but didn&amp;#8217;t know much else about it at the time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, a few years later, I discovered that it was one of the few songs that my father and I both knew, and could play together on our guitars. Turned out he had probably heard it as recorded by The Country Gentlemen on their 1960 album, &lt;em&gt;Country Songs Old &amp;amp; New&lt;/em&gt;, or had simply heard this same group perform the song at one of their many shows at the Crossroads, outside of DC, a venue my dad was known to have frequented. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, I found the song included on the Rosanne Cash album &lt;em&gt;The List&lt;/em&gt;, the title referring to a list of essential American songs as identified by &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt; father, Johnny Cash. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, later, it just started to turn up everywhere. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Settin&apos; the Woods on Fire&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/settinapos-the-woods-on-fire.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/settinapos-the-woods-on-fire.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;A couple of things that happened recently got me cogitating on the idea of language as playground. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I had a chance to hear &lt;a href=&quot;https://acurzan.english.lsa.umich.edu&quot;&gt;Anne Curzan&lt;/a&gt; speak. Curzan is the talented and engaging dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts at the University of Michigan (my alma mater), and is also a linguist who studies the history of the English language. Her bio states that she &amp;#8220;aims to promote a culture based in purpose and contributing to the common good, the power of learning, &lt;em&gt;the value of play&lt;/em&gt; [emphasis mine], and the importance of well-being.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I&amp;#8217;m here to tell you: any time you stir together the value of play and the study of the English language in the same pitcher, you&amp;#8217;re mixing up a cocktail that I will happily imbibe. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;And When I Die&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/and-when-i-die.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/and-when-i-die.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;As children, our thoughts about death are stuff of dreams and fairy tales. As adults we learn to suppress these thoughts because we are busy getting on with things. But as teenagers, in this transition between nursery rhymes and real life, we tend to approach this topic with a frankness and curiosity that can be somewhat startling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laura Nyro wrote her song &amp;#8220;And When I Die&amp;#8221; at the age of 17, and her refreshing treatment of the subject shows none of the reverence or piety that we learn to adopt as adults. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s look over her lyrics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when I die and when I&amp;#8217;m dead, dead and gone,   &lt;br /&gt;
There&amp;#8217;ll be one child born and a world to carry on, to carry on.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m not scared of dying and I don&amp;#8217;t really care.   &lt;br /&gt;
If it&amp;#8217;s peace you find in dying, well, then let the time be near. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Hallelujah&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/hallelujah.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/hallelujah.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;The history of Leonard Cohen&amp;#8217;s song &amp;#8220;Hallelujah&amp;#8221; is a fascinating one. Cohen&amp;#8217;s songs had never really been embraced by the masses, and his first recording of &amp;#8220;Hallelujah&amp;#8221; in the early eighties was part of an album so lacking in obvious commercial appeal that the president of CBS Records responded to it by saying: &amp;#8220;What is this? This isn&amp;#8217;t pop music. We&amp;#8217;re not releasing it. This is a disaster.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That recording was released, however, a little later on a small independent label, but few people took note of the album or of this particular song. Even for Cohen&amp;#8217;s small set of fans, it did not seem like a particularly memorable recording. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then a funny series of events began to play out over the next couple of decades. John Cale, formerly of the Velvet Underground, and himself not a household name, recorded a version of the song for a Cohen tribute album in 1991. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;The Weight&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/the-weight.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/the-weight.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I recently came across the Playing for Change &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/ph1GU1qQ1zQ&quot;&gt;Song Around the World video&lt;/a&gt; of Robbie Robertson&amp;#8217;s composition &amp;#8220;The Weight,&amp;#8221; and it made me want to think &amp;#8211; and write! &amp;#8211; more deeply about how this song works, and what it means, and the timeless nature of its appeal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s just read the lyrics through first (and listen to the music), and then talk about it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled into Nazareth,    &lt;br /&gt;
Was feeling about half past dead.    &lt;br /&gt;
I just need some place     &lt;br /&gt;
Where I can lay my head.    &lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Hey, mister, can you tell me     &lt;br /&gt;
Where a man might find a bed?&quot;    &lt;br /&gt;
He just grinned and shook my hand,    &lt;br /&gt;
&amp;#8220;No&amp;#8221; was all he said.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a load off Fanny.    &lt;br /&gt;
Take a load for free.      &lt;br /&gt;
Take a load off Fanny,     &lt;br /&gt;
And (and) (and) you put the load right on me.    &lt;br /&gt;
(You put the load right on me)    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up my bag,   &lt;br /&gt;
I went looking for a place to hide.    &lt;br /&gt;
When I saw Carmen and the Devil    &lt;br /&gt;
Walking side by side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;800 Pound Jesus&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/800-pound-jesus.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/800-pound-jesus.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2019 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;d been aware of Paul Thorn for some time, but didn&amp;#8217;t really become a fan until I saw him live last summer at The Ark in Ann Arbor. I convinced an old University of Michigan roommate to come with me while I was in town, as an opportunity to catch up, but we were both caught off guard by how much we loved Thorn&amp;#8217;s show. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been listening to Thorn&amp;#8217;s recordings regularly since then, and can now bear witness to a great catalog that stands up to deep and repeated listening.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musically Thorn reminds me of Delbert McClinton and a few other artists who have somewhat belatedly been collected under the &lt;em&gt;Americana&lt;/em&gt; banner. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Fruitcakes&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/fruitcakes.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/fruitcakes.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2018 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;From the Dictionary app on my iMac: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;fruitcake: 1. A cake containing dried fruit and nuts. 2. (informal) an eccentric or insane person. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve always considered &amp;#8220;Fruitcakes&amp;#8221; to be Jimmy Buffet&amp;#8217;s masterwork. The musical backing is infectious, swaying and danceable, and the background vocals add depth. The words are cleverly crafted, and perfectly suited to Buffett&amp;#8217;s conversational, wisecracking delivery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song is from 1993, and contains some dated references, but these just add to the fun for me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The singer starts with a spoken introduction, setting up the verses that will follow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know I was talking to my friend Desdemona the other day. She runs this space station bake shop down near Boomtown. She told me that human beings are flawed individuals, that the cosmic bakers took us out of the oven a little too early, and that&amp;#8217;s the reason we&amp;#8217;re as crazy as we are, and I believe it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note what Buffett is doing here. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;The Village Green Preservation Society&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/the-village-green-preservation-society.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/the-village-green-preservation-society.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This is a rather amazing song by The Kinks, first released in 1968. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved this song from the moment I first heard it, but my appreciation for it has only grown over the years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the same year that John Lennon and Yoko Ono released an album called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unfinished_Music_No._1:_Two_Virgins&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two Virgins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (certainly using the term to refer to themselves metaphorically, not literally), with an album cover showing the two artists completely naked, Ray Davies wrote a song with the immortal line, &amp;#8220;God save little shops, china cups and virginity&amp;#8221; (and Davies, to be clear,  delivered this line quite seriously and quite literally); &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Will the Circle be Unbroken&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/will-the-circle-be-unbroken.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/will-the-circle-be-unbroken.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;I first heard this song as the title track on the monumental 1972 album by the Nitty Gritty Dirt Band, which they recorded with a number of country music greats who were still alive at the time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This song is usually recorded under the title of &amp;#8220;Will the Circle be Unbroken,&amp;#8221; but it&amp;#8217;s also known by the name &amp;#8220;Can the Circle be Unbroken.&amp;#8221; The song was the result of a reworking by A.P. Carter of the hymn &amp;#8220;Will the Circle be Unbroken?.&amp;#8221; The song was first released in 1935, on a single by the Carter Family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of wonderful recordings of this song that I can recommend. I&amp;#8217;ll list them in chronological sequence. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Box of Rain&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/box-of-rain.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/box-of-rain.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;The music for this song was composed by Grateful Dead bassist Phil Lesh, with lyrics by Robert Hunter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunter wrote the words in response to a request from Lesh to help write a song he could sing to his dying father. The song first appeared on the album &lt;em&gt;American Beauty&lt;/em&gt;, released in 1970. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several unusual aspects to the band&amp;#8217;s performance on this track. Lesh plays acoustic guitar, Dave Torbert plays bass,  David Nelson plays lead guitar on a Fender Telecaster, while Jerry Garcia plays the piano. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s a rich track musically, with intertwining voices and instruments, so it&amp;#8217;s best to hear it in as uncompressed and high-fidelity a fashion as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note about this song is that, although Hunter could have responded to Lesh&amp;#8217;s request with some very specific words about a child sitting with a dying parent, he instead generalized and broadened the song&amp;#8217;s scope to instead speak to all of us about the meaning of life and death. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Girl From The North Country&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/girl-from-the-north-country.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/girl-from-the-north-country.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2017 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This is a deft example of the songwriter&amp;#8217;s art. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dylan has such an inimitable bag of tricks that many of his songs are unmistakably marked as his, either through attitude, theme, use of language, unusual length, or some combination of these factors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, though, Dylan is like a master magician: even after you&amp;#8217;ve taken away all the props, and had him roll up his sleeves, he can still effortlessly reach behind your ear and come back with a gold doubloon in his hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No railing against authority here, no diverse, divergent set of cultural references, no rolling series of verses, no hallucinatory imagery, no put-downs, no fancy words. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet Dylan still manages to produce a masterpiece. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s review the lyrics. It won&amp;#8217;t take long. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;If I Had a Boat&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/if-i-had-a-boat.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/if-i-had-a-boat.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2015 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This has always been my favorite Lyle Lovett recording. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The singer starts with the chorus, which is then repeated after each verse. Both musically and lyrically, it starts out as a simple children&amp;#8217;s song, with gentle, bright finger-picking on the guitar. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had a boat,  &lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;#8217;d go out on the ocean.  &lt;br /&gt;
And if I had a pony,   &lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;#8217;d ride him on my boat.  &lt;br /&gt;
And we could all together  &lt;br /&gt;
go out on the ocean,  &lt;br /&gt;
Me upon my pony on my boat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chorus is clearly from the perspective of a young child. Each line is simple and short, the rhyming consisting only of the repeated use of the word &amp;#8220;boat.&amp;#8221; Note that Lovett&amp;#8217;s singing is straightforward, sincere and heartfelt. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the first verse, though, Lovett shifts gears, taking a slightly older, more ironic perspective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I were Roy Rogers,  &lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;#8217;d sure enough be single.   &lt;br /&gt;
I couldn&amp;#8217;t bring myself to marrying old Dale.   &lt;br /&gt;
It&amp;#8217;d just be me and Trigger.  &lt;br /&gt;
We&amp;#8217;d go riding through them movies,   &lt;br /&gt;
Then we&amp;#8217;d buy a boat and on the sea we&amp;#8217;d sail. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;White Room&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/white-room.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/white-room.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2009 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This song was a huge hit single for Cream, off their &lt;em&gt;Wheels of Fire&lt;/em&gt; album. Lyricist Pete Brown says of the track, &amp;#8220;It was a miracle it worked, considering it was me writing a monologue about a new flat&amp;#8221; &lt;a href=&quot;#cn:1&quot; id=&quot;cnref:1&quot; title=&quot;see citation&quot; class=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt;. Let’s take a look at the words Brown wrote about his new accommodations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the white room, with black curtains, near the station,  &lt;br /&gt;
Black roof country, no gold pavements, tired starlings,  &lt;br /&gt;
Silver horses ran down moonbeams in your dark eyes.  &lt;br /&gt;
Dawn light smiles on you leaving, my contentment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll wait in this place where the sun never shines;  &lt;br /&gt;
Wait in this place where the shadows run from themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You said no strings could secure you at the station.  &lt;br /&gt;
Platform ticket, restless diesels, goodbye windows.  &lt;br /&gt;
I walked into such a sad time at the station.  &lt;br /&gt;
As I walked out, felt my own need just beginning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll wait in the queue when the trains come back; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;citations&quot;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;cn:1&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sandford:1999 &lt;a href=&quot;#cnref:1&quot; title=&quot;return to body&quot; class=&quot;reversecitation&quot;&gt;&amp;#160;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Stringing Me Along&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/stringing-me-along.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/stringing-me-along.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2009 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This song by Jess Chambers won the &amp;#8220;Best New Zealand Country Song&amp;#8221; award in 2009 so, even though Jess is my niece, I have no reservations in recommending it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t know that Jess would ever describe herself as a country singer, but she certainly had a chance to hear some country tunes while growing up in Southern California close to her American grandfather. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;#8217;t help but think that Jess had her tongue at least a little bit in cheek when writing these lyrics &amp;#8211; although it&amp;#8217;s clearly in a different position when she&amp;#8217;s singing them &amp;#8211; describing, as she does, a woman attracted to a man who has so little interest in her. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/z5xqWoPVZR4&quot;&gt;YouTube video&lt;/a&gt; nicely captures the spirit of the sessions that produced the album on which the song is featured. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Like A Rolling Stone&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/like-a-rolling-stone.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/like-a-rolling-stone.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2009 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have the audacity to play “Like A Rolling Stone” in my show, just about every night. I did it as a lark, to show off to some of the guys in my band that I knew all the words. But I was immediately struck by the audience response to the song. From six-year-olds to seventy-year-olds — &lt;em&gt;they all know the chorus to that song.&lt;/em&gt; I couldn’t put it away; every night, it’s a unifying thing. I think it’s somehow part of the fabric of our culture. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Country singer Rodney Crowell &lt;a href=&quot;#cn:1&quot; id=&quot;cnref:1&quot; title=&quot;see citation&quot; class=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Like A Rolling Stone” is not only one of the most popular rock songs of all time, it is also one of those whose appeal is the most mysterious. Whereas it is easy to see how other Dylan songs became anthems for a generation — songs like “Blowin’ in the Wind,” “The Times They Are A-Changing” and “Mr. Tambourine Man” — it is harder to see how this song attained such a broad and enthusiastic audience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;citations&quot;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;cn:1&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus:2005 &lt;a href=&quot;#cnref:1&quot; title=&quot;return to body&quot; class=&quot;reversecitation&quot;&gt;&amp;#160;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Christmas (Baby Please Come Home)&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/christmas-baby-please-come-home.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/christmas-baby-please-come-home.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2009 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;The lyrics in this song work so well because of their simple understatement. As in the title, the single word “Christmas” is repeated by the background choir to begin each line of the song. Darlene Love then describes, in the briefest of sketches, familiar elements of Christmas: “The snow’s coming down,” “Lots of people around,” “Pretty lights on the trees,” etc. Each verse ends with the same line: “(Christmas) Baby, Please Come Home!” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chorus fills in the sketchiest of details. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re singing “Deck the Halls,”  &lt;br /&gt;
But it’s not like Christmas at all,  &lt;br /&gt;
’Cause I remember when you were here,  &lt;br /&gt;
And all the fun we had last year! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s all we’re told really. Boy and girl together last Christmas. Boy and girl not together this Christmas. Girl misses boy. So the apparent conflict is in their separation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s something else going on here. There is no happy ending. The boy never shows up. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Come On In My Kitchen&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/come-on-in-my-kitchen.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/come-on-in-my-kitchen.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2009 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;This song is a great example of Johnson’s craft. Let’s look at the seemingly simple lyrics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mmm mmm mmm mmm mmm mmm mmm mmm mmm mmm mmm…  &lt;br /&gt;
Mmm mmm mmm mmm mmm mmm mmm mmm mmm.  &lt;br /&gt;
You better come on in my kitchen:  &lt;br /&gt;
Babe, it’s goin’ to be rainin’ outdoors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, the woman I love, took from my best friend.  &lt;br /&gt;
Some joker got lucky, stole her back again.  &lt;br /&gt;
You better come on in my kitchen:  &lt;br /&gt;
Baby, it’s goin’ to be rainin’ outdoors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh-ah, she’s gone… I know she won’t come back.  &lt;br /&gt;
I’ve taken the last nickel out of her nation sack.  &lt;br /&gt;
You better come on in my kitchen:  &lt;br /&gt;
Babe, it’s goin’ to be rainin’ outdoors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, can’t you hear that wind howl?  &lt;br /&gt;
Oh, can’t you hear that wind howl?  &lt;br /&gt;
You better come on in my kitchen:  &lt;br /&gt;
Babe, it’s goin’ to be rainin’ outdoors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a woman gets in trouble, everybody throws her down.  &lt;br /&gt;
Lookin’ for her good friend, none can be found. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

		</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Appreciation for the song &quot;Education&quot;</title>
		<link>https://lexiconofsong.org/education.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://lexiconofsong.org/education.html</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2005 00:00 PDT</pubDate>
		<description>
			&lt;p&gt;Chief among this song’s many pleasures is Ray Davies’ largely successful attempt to encapsulate the entire history of human civilization within the first three verses. The recording is also an excellent example of how Ray can change characters and perspectives many times within the same song. In addition, the song demonstrates Ray’s ability to shield his main theme within multiple layers of story and character, until he is ready to fully state it. In this way, he keeps us as listeners always amused, yet always off-guard, never quite sure where he is headed until he suddenly reveals his underlying intentions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opening drums, along with slashing guitar and organ chords, are slow, powerful and raw, suggesting primitive forces running loose at the dawn of creation. This accompaniment is almost immediately replaced, however, by a cautious, cantering piano riff. &lt;/p&gt;
		</description>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
